a Bonin is a three-time Arnold Classic
Champion he has more titles than anybody
else in this event in strong man is he
the favorite to win David is he the
favor to
win great to see Rudy only getting
stronger a as he hits the mid-70s he's
kind of competing against himself I
think if he wants to rewrite the record
books it's his for the taking actually a
lot of veterans coming back from World
War II were pretty instrumental in this
Muscle Beach era out on the west coast
of the United States when you think
silver era of bodybuilding you know what
do you think and kind of what comes to
your
mind Hey folks and welcome to strength
weekly the weekly show here on the
YouTubes that keeps you updated with
everything from around the barbell game
for barbend
docomomo and I'm joined by the
incomparable Phil bman before we get
into the week's top stories make sure
you subscribe to barbin on YouTube the
very digital platform you're watching
right now we have we have a massive
massive post Thanksgiving show for you
just like our gains here is the Run of
show we have our good friend Rudy CAD
absolutely keeping the Master's
powerlifting division in a headlock and
setting some alltime World Records along
the way we have the rosters for both the
men and women for the Arnold strongman
classic and not to be outdone and to put
those Gams to good use we are breaking
down every historic era of bodybuilding
which is one of the more interesting
segments we we've ever done and hey the
research was quite fun I spent a lot of
time on Muscle Beach in my head Phil
bman how many pounds of lean mass did
you gain over Thanksgiving my entire
body is now post Thanksgiving lean mass
David I'm monan mass now well the people
on this broadcast can't actually see me
from the chest down but let's just say I
went from classic physique to mass
monster that is all I am really going to
say but we're not talking about Mass
monsters we're talking about epically
strong people our good friend Rudy out
of the Great Pacific Northwest
absolutely continues his tear perhaps
the last time we see him compete as a 74
year old before he takes the 75 to 79
Division and absolutely throttles it
Phil Rudy cadb of Kabuki strength set
some all-time World Records recently uh
give us the breakdown of exactly what he
did and why it's historically important
so actually two things about his world
records he set three World Records on
during his performance two of them were
IPL World Records so specifically within
the international powerlifting League he
set a squat record of 27 a half
kilograms and a deadlift record of 235
kilograms but notably his total of 590
kilograms was the alltime world record
across all federations and that was the
goal that he had planned to set out
before he even went into the competition
he called that shot before he went in he
executed as as expected now he has the
Masters world record in the 70 to 74 m
category in the 100 kilogram weight
class and it's very exciting Rudy is
built different because often times we
see powerlifter post big training lifts
and they don't quite hit those or
they'll hit you know one or two kilos
within one or two kills of what they
need to set a record or win a
competition he blasted through that
let's compare the training lift if you
don't mind to what he actually did on
the platform yeah in the in his training
lift he scored 213 kilograms which was
at the time his max lift what he was
prepping for to do uh at least the IPL
world record and he breezes past that by
4 and a half kilograms on his final
squat this was like I think his piece to
resistance on his uh career in this
Division and you know maybe he had some
left in the tank you know like 217 and a
half is way more than I think you know
he he had planned to lift but he called
it for the barbell if you watch his
lifts back which are posted on his
Instagram page right now as we speak it
doesn't look like he struggled you know
I mean the guys the guys just built
different great to see Rudy um only
getting stronger as he hits the mid 70s
so uh really excited to see what he's
able to do in the next Masters category
he's kind of competing against himself I
think if he wants to rewrite the record
books it's his for the taking based on
the list that he's doing now I mean if
he goes any 75 next year and he just
competes at IPL worlds again and just
calls for similar numbers on the bar I
mean he he crushes all the world records
well Phil let's segue because this is
something that's going to predict your
March 2024 and that is the Arnold
strongman classic for both the men and
women so the Arnold the 2024 Arnold
strongman classic and strong woman
classic rosters have been revealed they
are both stacked to the traps is what
we're going to say we have defending
Champions historically great competitors
and on both sides we have some athletes
coming back from I'm not going to say
full retirement but semi-retirement or
at least folks who had taken a step back
from the top level competition they're
chopping at the bit to get back back to
that Elite level we can talk about this
for hours we don't have hours I am still
digesting Thanksgiving dinner and we'll
certainly have to take a nap after this
but we do want to talk about both these
divisions we'll start with the men then
move to the women Phil who on the men's
side for the 2024 Arnold strongman
Classic roster sticks out to you
immediately there are some juicy targets
we have defending Champion Mitchell
Hooper who is the 2023 World's Strongest
Man the 2023 Rogue Invitational Champion
he won the Arnold Classic last year he's
returning to defend that title he had a
couple of injuries throughout the year
but that did not slow him down since he
is the guy to beat second we also have
uh Martin's Le's returning again so
Martine has been on this on andof uh
sort of cadence where he competes for
one year crushes everything takes a year
off recovers from injury comes back
crushes everything he's going to try and
take down Mitchell Hooper Le he's won
the Arnold Classic in 2022 two Champions
back-to-back years Le's never defended
the title he didn't compete in 2023 so
this will be a fun match up between
those two okay let's talk about the big
return in haor bjon now haor bjon is a
three-time Arnold Classic Champion he
has more titles than anybody else in
this event in strongman is he the
favorite to win David is he the favorite
to win no no I don't think he's the
favorite to win I don't think he's the
favorite to win and I I I don't think
it's I don't think he's the favorite to
win and I don't think it's close now
that is not to say that is not to say
that he couldn't Podium Guy's Big guy's
still strong but for haor to come back
after losing a ton of weight to go into
boxing then move back into strongman at
you know a 100 kilos less than he was I
expect him to post maybe a fifth or six
Place finish and that would be great for
a comeback because even though he'll
never compete again at World's Strongest
Man he has he had a falling out with
giants live I would be very surprised if
they reconciled that uh this will be the
biggest show that we see ha Thor return
in alongside the Rogue Invitational if
bjon comes back and scores anywhere near
the podium like if he's in the top half
of the field that's exceptional for a
return He took a couple years off to uh
beat up Eddie Hall in the boxing ring he
did accomplish that he beat Eddie Hall
pretty soundly but he also took a little
detour after that uh into powerlifting
ended up getting injured injured his PEC
so not only is he coming back from
significant weight loss switching Sports
and by the way like kudo's the hotor he
was a real boxer right like he put in
put in the work he changed his physique
like he didn't just kind of phone it in
and box for a few months for I mean he
really took it seriously I do want to
point out the Arnold Classic is always
known for being the realm of static
monsters right it tends to be the
heaviest event in men's open strong man
and it tends to lean toward the guys who
are really good at the static of it
really heavy kind of standing in place
stuff let's just put it that way Bon's
more of a special event here than he is
a contender but if he does perform well
here and change the dynamic for what we
can expect for the 2024 Rogue
Invitational I think that's really
exciting which of the Americans would
you give the best shot at poding making
the podium here Lees Lees has this way
of I think doing strongman really
intelligently where guys guys that just
run show to show to show to show end up
slowing down or getting injured in some
way because they either burn out from
all the travel or you know they don't
fully recover from you know maybe micro
tears or other injuries that they
suffered during the competition we saw
that with novakov right he was crushing
just like Podium Podium Podium Podium
and then lately he's been in the bottom
half he's been getting injured he got
injured at the 20203 world strongest B
in his best event and then since then he
just hasn't posted up numbers that's not
to say that he's not good enough anymore
I think he just never took the time to
fully recover because he kept going from
event to event I would agree with that
let's move on to the women uh Phil uh
give me a couple names or a few names
that stick out to you on the women's
side and we could talk about every
competitor on this list but give me your
your immediate reaction highlights here
if Victoria long doesn't win gold I it
might be the upset of the Year even
though it's happening in the first
quarter you have some absolute uh
Haymaker Stars here I mean OAS could
crush any event she's in Angelica
Jardine has been showing up pretty well
in the last couple events Melissa
peacock is usually pretty good in static
events Andrea Thompson and Donna Moore
are both former world's strongest women
Champions and they could show up at any
event and do really well I mean Andrea
Thompson specifically in overhead events
could do exceptionally well so if they
do a match log lift or anything like
that that's easy points for Andrea uh
Lucy underdown has been deadlifting like
an absolute monster recently tomarrow
Walcott is coming back in and she has
proven in her powerlifting career to be
an exceptional deadlifter Hannah Lindsay
just scored a world record at the Rogue
record Breakers fents at the Thor hammer
like these are hitters I think Victoria
long just was so dominant last year that
anything less than that would be
surprising more so than for the men for
the women I think the events are going
to be really influential as to who's
going to be able to score points
where let's move on to the world of
bodybuilding because we all just ate way
too many calories and uh we got to
figure out where we're going to do with
that where we're going to put on the
mass and uh where we're going to have
regrets don't regret eating holiday
meals folks uh as long as you enjoy
yourself and uh you know give gratitude
for your friends and family etc etc this
isn't therapy this is bodybuilding let's
talk about the eras of bodybuilding Dr
Conor Heenan who I believe is one of the
world's most prominent preeminent and
premium strength historians wrote a
great article for Barb and breaking down
the historic eras of bodybuilding well
let's start with the first era it's the
bronze era which is kind of the
development of the first stage of modern
bodybuilding and you could draw a line
between the 1890s to the 1920s and there
wasn't a whole lot of differentiation at
that time between bodybuilding and other
strength sports right people lifting
weights was kind of one category some
big figures Katie Sandu Eugene Sandow
and I give those in reverse order
because Sandu got her stage name from
sand out George hacken Schmid if you've
ever done a hack squat you're welcome
but also apologies Arthur Saxon these
are all big Pioneers in the kind of
circus era of bodybuilding but they're
really taking it from being kind of a
sideshow thing to strength training and
weightlifting being a legitimate Pursuit
so the bronze era of bodybuilding really
sets the stage and there's kind of a bit
of a pause because the bronze era
bodybuilding goes up to the 20s and then
you don't really have silver era of
bodybuilding until the 40s really post
World War II so you have this period of
a couple decades at least worldwide
where the focus necessar wasn't
necessarily on athletic culture or at
least on strength training because I
don't know World Wars and such but
coming out of World War II you do see
the Silver age of bodybuilding develop
and ha in his article um reflects that
actually a lot of veterans coming back
from World War II were pretty
instrumental in this Muscle Beach era
out on the west coast of the United
States when you think silver era of
bodybuilding you know what do you think
and kind of what comes to your mind I
mean Bill Pearl is like the I feel like
the iconic name for me in that in in in
the in the roster that we have of that
era the aesthetic really followed
culture it followed pop culture to to a
big degree I mean you got to think at
this time this is also like TV is coming
in cinema is coming in like as that
stuff gradu like evolves so too does
bodybuilding and the clout of which
becoming a bodybuilder has and so you as
we go into Golden Era and you see like
the action superstars of like these
thick bodybuilders that are like you
know heavy metal looking like rock dudes
in action movies you know that's
different from the sort of like
picturesque uh you know cover models of
the silver era I think bodybuilding is
uniquely tied to culture in that way and
it's it's like really really
demonstrative in the in the sequencing
of this if you look at it and that leads
us to the Golden Era of bodybuilding
which is from the' 60s arguably to the
late 80s although I've heard it debated
as to exactly which time strips the
Golden Era encapsulated this is where we
see bodybuilding in many ways go
mainstream and that is in large part to
the movie Pumping Iron which follows
Schwarzenegger fno and Columbo um you
know leading up to the Mr uh Olympia
contest and it's the first look that a
lot of mainstream audiences get into the
bodybuilding lifestyle not just what do
these folks look like but what goes into
to achieving those physiques you also
have concurrently the development of
different nutritional supplements some
of the first bodybuilding and strength
nutritional supplements coming onto the
market and we got to say it I don't want
to speculate too much I'm not going to
like pretend to know the exact stacks
these athletes were using but
performance enhancers not only in
bodybuilding but across Sports this is
where you see performance enhancers
really become part of certain Sports in
the Olympic movement right you see a lot
of States sponsored doping here yeah and
and bodybuilding is now one of the
sports where it's like of course all the
athletes are enhanced it's no longer
like the secret or taboo for
bodybuilders to be enhanced athletes
like we as a culture have also evolved
with that around the sport uh I do want
to touch on the Golden Era uh and how
you had just talked about uh them
becoming in in movies and pumping iron
and everything like that there's a uh a
well-known interview Arnold
Schwarzenegger did where he has the
interviewee FIS bicep and his bicep is
obviously like a gigantic mountain peak
and he's like he's like look at this
mountain look at this bicep it's an unel
and the thing is is that it's portrayed
as alien right it's like oh my God this
guy is of another world this is
different than what we can expect from
any human person and that if you if you
if you look at it in that lens even
though it's done in an interview on
television is similar to the guys in the
the circus ERA with Sandow and Louis
Seer where it's like they are portrayed
as alien figures because they're so
strong they're like the strong men on
the side of the circus whereas here
they're just the strong men literally
live on television so so to this day we
talk about these guys as otherworldly
for what they're able to accomplish with
their physiques that's that's the one
through line that has been stay static
all the way through with uh every
era let's move on to the most
controversial era in bodybuilding I'm
going to read a quote from Dr heffernon
here the most controversial bodybuilding
era is the mass monster era from the
late 1980s to 2010 this was a time when
bodybuilders pushed the absolute
boundaries of muscle gain and in the
view of some individuals began to
sacrific Aesthetics for sheer mass or
extreme leanness this era also coincided
with controversies surrounding steroids
and other performance-enhancing drugs
and sports culminating in the United
States passing the anabolic steroid
Control Act of 1990 which classified
anabolic steroids as a controlled
substance and subject to tight
government regulations this led to the
one and only drug test in Mr Olympia in
September 1990 which Lee Haney won uh
the mass monster era is what I grew up
with in bodybuilding so you have
athletes pushing the absolute limits
literally trying to get as wide and
massive um as possible a controversial
era indeed and some would say a very
dangerous era in uh in bodybuilding
history pH uh what comes to mind for you
when you think of the mass monster era I
look at it now as trying to figure out
what the line is for bodybuilding as as
a whole we didn't know how far the
athletes could take it you know I think
one of the guys that comes to mind for
me in you know sort of going up to that
line and then coming back is Big Ramy
you know big Ramy was known as like the
biggest guy on the stage at all times
and he never really found really great
success until the past couple of years
when he like leaned back down a little
bit and like got got got away from like
that far- ranging line of like being the
biggest biggest biggest biggest
possible well let's talk about the
modern era which uh he which Dr heon
defines is kind of 2010 on it's the
current ERA we're in obviously and it's
an ER era that I think will probably
change names we'll look back on this in
40 years and refer to it as something
else but for right now it's kind of what
we're in and there is a little bit of a
dialing back a movement away from Pure
Mass monsters and more toward aesthetic
balanced proportional physiques part of
that coincides with the introduction
during this time of new divisions
including classic physique Chris bum
said the Canadian Phenom five-time
defending champion in that category
arguably the biggest name in
bodybuilding you also get the
introduction of the wellness division a
new women's category that has seen uh
monstrous growth really in only a few
years of actually being um a a division
at the highest levels of bodybuilding it
is a step up from bikini athletes are
allowed to carry a bit more mass
especially in their lower bodies you do
see a lot of athletes moving not only
from other bodybuilding divisions but
from other sports you see a number of
powerlifters moving from women's
powerlifting over to Wellness as kind of
an entry point uh because they don't
necessarily get penalized for having
more developed lower bodies the modern
era who who are some names that stick
out to you uh Phil besides bums Dead who
has really Define the classic buy
category who are some names that stick
out to you um that help Define the
modern era I think Brion Ansley really
defined what that was he's a two-time
champion and his sort of like very clean
Aesthetics from top to bottom you know
Exquisite posing he really helped sculpt
what that uh division became and then
Bumstead was second to him a couple
years in a row before taking the mantle
and never letting it goon really lay lay
the foundation for the division for
bumpstead to then Thrive Phil on the
men's open side which bodybuilders for
you encapsulate the modern era so what
we saw for the last handful of years we
saw big Ramy who like lean down he took
two year two titles in a row then we saw
Supreme conditioning take the throne and
hadti Chapan wins his title we come back
this year Lunsford after coming off a
silver a silver medal finish in his
debut in the open after moving up from
212 and the difference between him was
he has that that wide shoulder very
narrow waist like his physique flows
much smoother right from from the
shoulders down to the x-frame like he's
got that look now does he went on
conditioning maybe not as close as hotti
but as we've seen in the last couple of
years they've moved steadily towards the
lunsford's look the thing that jumps out
to me is one year Arnold Schwarzenegger
was in the commentary booth at the
Olympia and he was fawning over the
classic physique Olympia guys he was
like just enamored by bumstead's
physique he was like this is
bodybuilding this is what it should look
like and he was advocating in the booth
for classic physique to become the
biggest division at the Olympia it's
going towards the bigger classic
physique rather than the mass monster I
think we're moving towards a more flowy
aesthetic Direction and when we look
back I think like the modern era will be
renamed to something like that like the
classic era you know well if you want to
learn more about every era of
bodybuilding including the one we're
currently in as yet to be named uh
beyond the modern era make sure you read
the article by Dr heon and you can do
that by going to Barb and.com or
clicking on the link in the description
below uh super super easy we want to
make it smooth for you like Derek
lunsford's physique as Phil would say
well folks I hope you had a lovely
holiday with friends family or alone
avoiding both of those groups of people
until then for strength weekly I'm David
Thomas to joined by Phil bman of farb
ben.com thankk you guys so much for
joining us on our post Thanksgiving
episode we hope you enjoyed and we will
catch you next time still filling full
[Music]
folks